Guide to the Student Army Training Corps, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Student Army Training Corps, Yale University, records
1911-1921
RU 88
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.25
The records consist of correspondence, administrative records, student records, financial records, photographs, scrapbooks, clippings, and memorabilia documenting the Army and Navy training programs at Yale up to 1919. Records concerning the following programs are included: Yale Battery, Reserve Officers Training Corps (ROTC and NROTC), Yale Naval Training Unit, and the Student Army Training Corps (SATC).
Yale University. Student Army Training Corps
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 42-A (YRG 42-A), Records of military training programs at Yale.
Arrangement
The records are arranged in two series: I. Army Training Programs. II. Yale Naval Training Unit.
Scope and Contents
The Yale Battery was organized in the fall of 1915 under the direction of General Leonard Wood. It rapidly grew into four batteries, which were mustered into the Connecticut 10th Field Artillery of the National Guard.
After the National Defense Act of June 3, 1916 provided for the establishment of R.O.T.C. units on college campuses, Yale moved to replace these militia batteries with a regular R.O.T.C. program. In Feb. 1917 the R.O.T.C. program at Yale was instituted, under the direction of Captain Robert Danford. The Yale Naval Training Unit (originally the Motor Boat Patrol), was also officially organized at this time, under the direction of Mather Abbott.
In the spring of 1918, existing R.O.T.C. programs were suspended and replaced with the Student Army Training Corps. This was a program designed to establish military training units in the colleges and to substitute specialized instruction for the normal curriculum. All students, except those with 4-F draft board ratings, were to belong to it; all non-militarily useful courses were to be suspended for the duration of the war; students would be subject to military regulations. The existing R.O.T.C. programs (Army & Navy), would be co-ordinated by the S.A.T.C.
The S.A.T.C. began at Yale Oct. 1, 1918, after a summer of intensive preparation by the University and War Department. However, the program only existed for the fall of 1918. After the armistice on Nov. 11, the S.A.T.C. appeared to have lost its purpose, and it was ordered demobilized by Congress in Nov. 26, 1918. The R.O.T.C. programs were re-established at Yale in February of 1919.
The papers are divided into 2 series: Series I contains the papers of all Army Training Programs at Yale (the Battery, the S.A.T.C., and the R.O.T.C.), and Series II concerns Naval Training Programs. The papers are arranged alphabetically by topic, and chronologically within each topic. Correspondence in all cases includes general memoranda sent by the War Department as well as Yale correspondence. The S.A.T.C. material also includes, under correspondence, the bulletins sent to S.A.T.C. units by the Committee on Education and Special Training (War Department).
Biographical / Historical
The Yale Battery was the first Army training program established at Yale in 1915. Eventually Yale had four batteries which became the Connecticut 10th Field Artillery of the National Guard. In 1916, Yale replaced its batteries with the Reserve Officers Training Corps (ROTC) and the Yale Naval Training Unit (originally the Motor Boat Patrol and later known as NROTC). In the Spring of 1918, existing ROTC programs were suspended and replaced with the Student Army Training Corps (SATC). The program was designed to establish military training units in colleges and to substitute specialized military training for the normal curriculum during World War I. Students were subject to military regulations and the existing ROTC programs (Army and Naval) were coordinated by the SATC. The SATC was demobilized by Congress in 1918. The ROTC programs were re-established at Yale in 1919.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research
Military training camps -- United States; Soldiers -- Education, Non-military -- United States; Universities and colleges -- Administration; World War, 1914-1918 -- Education and the war; World War, 1914-1918 -- War work -- Schools; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States; United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps; United States. Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps; Yale University -- Administration; Yale University -- Students; Yale University. Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps; Yale University. Reserve Officers' Training Corps; Yale University. Student Army Training Corps
- Army Training Programs, Series I
  - Yale Battery
    - Mess Accounts--1916 Jul-Sep (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Mess Accounts--[1916?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mess Supplies Ledger, 1916 July (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Record Book & Vouchers, 1916 July-1917 February (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Tenth Field Artillery,", 1917 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "Tenth Field Artillery and Naval Training at Yale,", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Yale R.O.T.C.
    - Information Book, Part I, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Information Book, Part II, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Information Book, Part III, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Information Book, Part IV, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Inventory of Ordnance Property, 1918 Jun, 1918 December (Box 6, Folder 11-13)
    - Inventory Correspondence, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - War Department Bulletins, 1919 January-July (Box 3, Folder 15-18)
    - "Yale R.O.T.C. Between the Wars" (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Yale S.A.T.C.--Student Army Training Corps
    - Correspondence, 1918 May-December (Box 4, Folder 20-26)
    - Course Preparations (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
    - Dining Hall Records, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Discharge Lists, 1918 December (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - Enrollment Information, 1918 October-1919 July (Box 5, Folder 31)
    - Enrollment and Battery Rosters, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 32)
    - Financial Records, 1918 September-1919 August (Box 5, Folder 33-35)
    - Hospital Costs; Correspondence, 1918 October-1919 October (Box 5, Folder 36)
    - Hospital Costs; Patient lists & Vouchers, 1918 (Box 5, Folder 37-38)
    - Orders, War Department, 1916-1918 (Box 6, Folder 39-40)
    - Pamphlets, 1918 (Box 6, Folder 41)
    - Reimbursement Forms, 1918-1919 (Box 6, Folder 42)
    - Miscellaneous & Unclassified (Box 6, Folder 43)
- Yale Naval Training Unit, Series II
  - Account Book, 1918 July-August (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Accounts, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Bills, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Check Ledgers & Financial Statements (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1917 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1918 May-1921 (Box 7, Folder 49-54)
  - Enlistment Information, 1917-1918 (Box 7, Folder 55)
  - Enrollment Rosters, 1918 (Box 7, Folder 56)
  - Food Service Records, 1918 June-August (Box 8, Folder 57-58)
  - Food Service Records, 1918-1920 (Box 8, Folder 59)
  - Log Book for the U.S.S. Belle, 1918 July-September (Box 8, Folder 60)
  - Order Book for the U.S.S. Belle, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 61)
  - Photographs, YNTU (Box 8, Folder 62)
  - Property Book for the U.S.S. Belle, 1918 (Box 8, Folder 63)
  - Receipts, 1918 June-November (Box 8, Folder 64-65)
  - Yale Naval Training Unit
    - Reimbursement correspondence, 1917-1919 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Reimbursement Forms (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Scrapbook (Box 9, Folder 68)
    - Scrapbook, loose clippings (Box 9, Folder 69)
    - Training Material "The Compass and its Errors" (Box 9, Folder 70)
    - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 9, Folder 71)